William Walden Rubey Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Speeches and Writings, 1923-1974 (Box 13-37)
  - Articles (Box 13)
    - 1968, “The Denver Earthquakes,” Science For additional material see Containers 45-47, Denver earthquakes (Box 25)
      - Research notes
        - Q's, △'s, daily earthquake magnitudes
        - Seismic magnitude and energy
        - TCO2, carbon and non-carbon
        - Thermal contraction
        - Time lag
          - Days, (2 folders)
          - Months
        - Transient earth strains
        - Van Poollen reports
        - Volcanic gas calculations
        - Water content and temperature of silicate melts
        - Well head pressure, injection volumes, and quakes
        - Z, confidence limits, etc., by days
      - Revisions
    - 1969, “Role of Cohesive Strength in the Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting and of Landsliding: Discussion,” Bulletin of the Geological Society of America (Box 27)
    - 1971, “Orogeny,” McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia
    - 1973, “New Cretaceous Formations in the Western Wyoming Thrust Belt,” Geological Survey Bulletin, United States Geological Survey
      - Correspondence and distribution list
      - Printed version
  - Biographical memoirs of colleagues
    - 1957, Charles K. Leith
    - 1970, Harry H. Hess
  - Book introductions
    - 1963, The Earth, Life Nature Library series
    - 1968, The Earth, Life Nature Library series
    - 1974, “Fifty Years of the Earth Sciences; A Renaissance,” introductory chapter to Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences
      - Correspondence, 1972-1974
      - Drafts
      - Notes
      - Printed version
  - Book reviews
    - 1934, The Deformation of the Earth's Crust, by Walter H. Bucher
    - 1941, Strength and Structure of the Earth, by Reginald A. Daly
    - 1966, Advances in Earth Sciences, ed. by P. M. Hurley
    - 1968, Government in Science: The U.S. Geological Survey, by Thomas G. Manning
  - Manuscripts critiqued by Rubey
    - 1926, “Oil Possibilities of the Black Hills Region,” by E. G. Sinclair
    - 1927, “The Effect of Gravitational Compaction on the Structure of Sedimentary Rocks,” by H. D. Hedberg
    - 1928, “The Compressibility of Sand-mica Mixtures,” by Glennon Gilby
    - 1935, “Sedimentary Size Frequency Curves,” by William C. Krumbein
    - 1941, “Some Experiments on the Transportation of Suspended Load,” by V. A. Vononi and “Rational Equation of River-bed Profile,” by S. A. Shulits
    - 1942, “Phosphorite Deposits on the Sea Floor off Southern California,” by R. S. Dietz, O. Emery, and F. P. Shepard, 1941-1942, (2 folders)
    - 1950, “Water in Primordial and Derivative Magma and its Relations to the Pre-forming Fluid,” by John D. Ridge (Box 28)
    - 1952, “Hypsometric Analysis of Erosional Topography,” by Arthur N. Strahler
    - 1954, “Role of Water in Metamorphism,” by Hatten S. Yoder, Jr.
    - 1960, “Evolution of Ocean Basins,” by Harry H. Hess
    - 1962, “The Sodium Cycle and the Age of the Ocean,” by D. A. Livingstone
      - Correspondence and drafts
      - Research notes, (7 folders)
    - 1963, “Rate of Growth of Continents,” by Frank A. Menard
    - 1968, “Geometric and Physical Sealing of River Dimensions on the Earth and Moon,” by J. J. Gilvarry
    - 1973, “The Amsden Formation (Mississippian and Pennsylvanian) of Wyoming,” by William J. Sando, MacKenzie Gordon, Jr., and J. T. Dutro, (4 folders) (Box 29)
    - Undated
      - “Mineralogy, Petrography, and Petrology of the Carbonate and Phosphate Rocks of the Phosphatic Shale Member of the Phosphoria Formation at Coal Canyon, Wyoming,” by R. A. Gulbrandsen
  - Miscellaneous writings
    - Critiques, 1946-1952, undated
    - Fragments, 1927-1932, undated
    - Letter with research notes to L. T. Aldrich, 1957
    - Manuscripts, undated (Box 30)
      - “Auburn Hot Springs”
        - Drafts
        - Research notes, (2 folders)
      - “Carbon Dioxide Equilibria and the Hydrogen Ion Concentration of Natural Surface Water”
      - “The Graded Slopes and Profiles and the Adjusted Cross-sections of Streams”
        - Drafts
        - Research notes, (3 folders)
      - “The Monoclines and Echelon Faults of the Western Flank of the Black Hills”
    - Notes of philosophical nature, relating to earth sciences, undated
    - Speech materials, 1962-1969
  - Press releases, United States Geological Survey, 1922-1926 (Box 31)
  - Reports, United States Geological Survey
    - 1923, “Progress Report on a Subsurface Study of the Pershing Oil and Gas Field, Osage County, Oklahoma”
    - 1936, “Mineral Resources of the Region around Boulder Dam”
    - 1967, “Chemical Composition of Sedimentary Rocks in Colorado, Kansas, Montana, Nebraska, North Dakota, South Dakota, and Wyoming”
      - Correspondence, 1956-1971, (2 folders)
      - Drafts
        - Chapter, “Statistical Summaries”, (2 folders)
        - Introduction, (2 folders)
      - Illustrative materials
      - Research notes
        - Average analyses of corefindings, (2 folders)
        - Carbons
        - Confidence limits
        - Data relating to Kansas, (2 folders) (Box 32)
        - Dixon and Massey
        - Equations and derivations
        - Future computations
        - Means and standard deviations
        - Miscellaneous
        - Nanz
        - Normal to lognormal conversion
        - Shaw, Nanz and Clarke
        - Shaw, pelitic rocks
        - Ss
        - Standard deviations
        - Student tests
        - t.975df
        - Tables, (2 folders)
        - Thickness and number analyses
  - Research materials
    - Airy roots
    - Common rock making constituents
    - Computations for compilations, (4 folders) (Box 33)
    - Cretaceous system in the Japanese islands
    - Depth of differentiation
    - Fossil fuel
    - Freedom station
    - Geology 262
    - Glaucophane schist
    - Graywacke computations
    - Gulf coast wells
    - Lake and stream waters
    - Metakaolinite, first trys
    - Metakaolinite, general
  - Research notes (Box 34)
    - Metakaolinite, reactions
    - Mineral formulas
    - Miscellaneous
    - Mm/Ms, (2 folders)
  - Speeches
    - 1926, Jan. 13, “Stream Piracy in North-eastern Wyoming,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - 1927, Feb. 9, “The Origin of the Mowry Shale,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - 1928, Jan. 11, “Possible Varves in Marine Cretaceous Shale in Wyoming,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - 1931
      - Feb. 25, “The Illinois River, a Problem in Channel Equilibrium,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
      - “A Need for Closer Cooperation among Students of Stream Work,” American Geophysical Union, Washington, D.C.
    - 1932, May 11, “Alluvial Islands: Their Origin and Effect upon Stream Regimen,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - 1933, “Equilibrium Conditions in Debris-laden Streams,” American Geophysical Union, Washington, D.C.
    - 1935, Apr. 10, “The Force Required to Move Particles on a Stream Bed,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - 1940, Feb. 28, “Chemical Evidence Bearing on Origin of a Group of Hot Springs,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - 1943, “Vanadiferous Shale in the Phosphoria Formation, Wyoming and Idaho,” American Institute of Mining and Metallurgical Engineers, New York, N.Y.
    - 1948, Dec., “The Problem of Changes in Composition of Sea Water and Atmosphere during the Geologic Past,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C. For additional material see Containers 15-18, 1951, “Geologic History of Sea Water”
    - 1949
      - Apr. 8, “Formation of the Earth's Atmosphere,” Historical Geophysics Seminar, Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
      - Apr. 13, “Possible Mechanism for Continuous Supply of Volatiles at the Earth's Surface,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C
      - Dec. 13, “Sea-water and Atmosphere through the Past: A Problem in General Geology,” Geological Conference, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
    - 1950
      - Jan., “Lines of Evidence for Estimating Volume of Primitive Ocean,” Unidentified group, Santa Fe, N. Mex.
      - Mar. 28, “The Problem of Origin of the Atmosphere and Ocean,” classroom lecture
      - Oct. 12, “Geologic Evidence regarding the Science of the Earth's Hydrosphere and Atmosphere,” National Academy of Sciences, Schenectady, N.Y., (2 folders)
      - Nov. 16, “Geologic History of Sea Water,” Geologic Society of America, Washington, D.C.
        - Drafts, (2 folders)
        - Notes and printed materials
    - 1951, “The Development of the Oceans and Atmosphere,” traveling lecture arranged by the American Association of Petroleum Geologists (Box 35)
    - 1952, “Seismic and Chemical Evidence on the Depth of Differentiation below the Continents,” Conference on Nuclear Abundances of Elements, Yerkes Observatory, Williams Bay, Wisc.
      - Agendas and correspondence
      - Drafts
      - Research notes, (2 folders)
    - 1953
      - Feb. 11, “Possible Tectonic Effects of Fractional Melting and Crustal Spreading,” Geological Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
        - Drafts
        - Research notes, (3 folders)
      - Apr. 11, “Hypothesis regarding the Origin of Continents and the Ocean,” South Carolina Academy of Sciences, Columbia, S.C.
      - May 5, “Tectonic Consequences of Crustal Growth by Selective Fusion,” American Geophysical Union, Washington, D.C.
      - June 9-11, “Geochemistry,” Conference on Biochemistry, Paleoecology, and Evolution, Shelter Island, N.Y.
      - Dec. 29, “The Origin of Ocean Water,” American Association for the Advancement of Science,” Boston, Mass.
    - 1954
      - Oct. 14, “The Development of the Hydrosphere and Atmosphere,” Crust of the Earth Symposium, Columbia University, New York, N.Y. See also Container 19, 1955, same title
      - Dec. 16, lecture given at Scripps Oceanographic Institute, San Diego, Calif.
      - Lectures given at the University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.
        - Drafts and outlines
        - Research notes
          - Melting order, (3 folders)
          - Radioactive heat, (2 folders) (Box 36)
          - Thermal gradients
          - White at U.C.L.A., (2 folders)
    - 1955
      - Oct. 20-22, “Role of Volatiles in Geological Process,” Geophysical Laboratory, Washington, D.C.
      - Lecture given at the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, Calif.
    - 1956, lectures given at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., (5 folders)
    - 1957 (Box 37)
      - July 15, “Partial Fusion of the Deep Interior as a Continuing Source of the Earth's Atmospheric Hydrosphere and Crust,” Shell Laboratories, Houston, Tex.
      - Nov. 5, “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting,” co-authored and presented with M. King Hubbert, Geological Society of America, Atlantic City, N.J. See also Containers 19-22, 1959, same title
        - Correspondence, 1956-1958
        - Drafts
    - 1962, Dec. 4, “Geochemistry of Sediments,” University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.
    - 1963, Nov. 20, “Possible Tectonic Significance of Transformation of Gypsum to Anhydride plus Water,” Geological Society of America
    - 1965
      - Apr. 19, “Mountain Building,” University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.
      - May 15, “Geology, Where, Wither?” University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
        - Correspondence and printed materials
        - Drafts and notes
    - 1967
      - Jan. 16, re overthrust tectonics, Colorado Scientific Society, Denver, Colo.
      - Apr. 3, “Waste Disposal and Earthquakes in the Denver area,” Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind.
      - Oct. 19-20, “The Geologic History of the Hydrosphere and Atmosphere,” Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo, Mich.
      - Oct. 28-29, “The Geologic History of the Hydrosphere and Atmosphere,” University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisc. For additional material see same container, 1967, Oct. 19-20
    - 1968
      - May 13, re Denver earthquakes, Scripps Oceanographic Institute, San Diego, Calif.
      - Aug. 7, re Denver earthquakes, Lockheed Propulsion Company Branch, Scientific Research Co. of America, Redlands, Calif.
      - Oct. 7, “Primitive Oceans and the Atmosphere,” Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
    - 1971, May 21, lecture on the history of science during the twentieth century
    - 1972, Aug. 25, “Mountain-making in Western Wyoming,” International Geologic Congress, Montreal, Canada
    - Undated, “Stream Piracy in Northeastern Wyoming,”
  - Television appearances, “The Rains Came,” episode of “Our World in Space,” 1956
- Subject File, 1915-1974 (Box 38-95)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, press releases, minutes of meetings, newspaper clippings, maps, photographs, and printed matter pertaining to Rubey's activities as a geologist for the United States Geological Survey and as a member of various scientific, professional, and educational organizations.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Academy of Natural Sciences (Box 38)
  - American Academy of Achievement, 1964
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1952-1973, 1964
    - Symposium on Climatic Change, 1952
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science
    - Commission on Science Education, 1968-1969
    - Committees
      - Committee on Arid Lands
        - Correspondence, 1971-1973
        - Meetings, 1972-1973
        - Position papers, 1972-1973
      - Committee on Desert and Arid Zone Research, 1959-1962, (2 folders)
      - Other committees, 1939-1961, (2 folders)
    - Conferences and symposia
      - International Oceanographic Conference
        - Agendas and memoranda, 1958-1959
        - Correspondence, 1957-1959
        - Notes, 1957-1959
      - Parliament of Science, 1958
      - Science and Man in the Americas, 1972-1973 (Box 39)
      - Symposium on the History of American Geology, 1958, (2 folders)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1947-1974
    - Meetings, 1961-1969, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1958, 1963
    - Newcomb Cleveland Prize, 1951-1961, (4 folders)
    - Philanthropic activities, 1957-1959 (Box 40)
    - Science editorial board, 1948-1972
  - American Association of Petroleum Geologists, 1946-1971
  - American Astronomical Society, 1969
  - American Geological Institute
    - Articles of organization, 1947-1950
    - Brochures, newsletters, and press releases, 1950-1954, undated
    - Committees
      - Evaluation Committee, 1959
      - Geological Society of America Committee on the Activities and Organization of the American Geological Institute, 1958-1959, (3 folders)
      - Reorganization Committee, 1959-1960, (2 folders)
      - Translation Committee, 1959 (Box 41)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1947-1964, (5 folders)
    - Minutes of meetings
      - Board of directors, 1947-1954, (3 folders)
      - Executive Committee, 1950-1953
    - Notes and miscellany, 1947-1953, undated
    - Reports, 1946-1959, (2 folders)
    - Transcript of proceedings of an informal assembly of thirteen geological organizations, 1945
    - Visiting geological scientist program, 1962-1963
  - American Geophysical Union (Box 42)
    - Bylaws and statutes, 1945
    - Committees
      - Committee on American Journal of Geophysics, 1936-1942
      - Committee on Dynamics of Streams
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1932-1948
        - Subcommittee on Land Forms, 1931-1943
        - Subcommittee on Sediment Terminology, 1933-1946
      - Committee on Meetings
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1935-1938, (2 folders)
        - Notes and miscellany, 1937-1938
      - Committee on Membership of the Union, 1938-1947
      - Committee on Nominations, 1945-1946
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1931-1973
    - Hydrology section, 1935-1936, 1961-1962
    - Lists of members, 1937-1938
    - Minutes of meetings, 1937-1938
    - Venus panel, 1947, 1969
    - Walter H. Bucher Medal, 1969
  - American Men of Science, 1958-1961 (Box 43)
  - American Philosophical Society
    - Committee on Meetings, 1959-1960
    - Correspondence, 1953-1960, 1970
    - Programs, lists, and other materials relating to meetings, 1952-1973, (5 folders)
  - Cambridge Radio Observatory, Cambridge, Mass., 1967
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - Board of Trustees, 1961-1973, (2 folders)
    - Chile telescope, 1964-1971, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Committee for Selection of a New President, 1969-1970
    - Conferences and symposia
      - Geophysical Laboratory Metamorphic Facies Symposium, 1956
      - Symposium honoring Caryl Haskins, 1970-1971
    - Correspondence and notes regarding reprint of “The California Earthquake of April 18, 1906"
    - Hale Observatory, Pasadena, Calif., 1970-1971
    - Miscellany, 1962-1972
    - Newsletters, 1971-1974
    - Press releases, 1969-1971
    - Tax exemption status, 1964-1971
  - Denver earthquakes (Box 45)
    - Advanced Research Projects Agency, Rangely study
      - Correspondence, 1969-1973
      - Meetings, 1969-1971, (2 folders)
      - Proposals, 1969
      - Reports, 1970
    - Background materials
      - Articles and newspaper clippings, 1966-1973
      - Research papers, undated
    - Colorado School of Mines, Golden, Colo.
      - Monthly reports of seismic activity, 1962-1970
      - Other reports, 1967, (2 folders)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1972
    - National Center for Earthquake Research, 1965-1966
    - Office of Science and Technology panel (Box 46)
      - Correspondence and notes, 1966, undated
      - Minutes of meetings, 1966, undated
      - Reports, 1967
    - Reports by consulting geologists
      - Rubey, 1966-1967, (3 folders)
      - Others, 1966, undated, (3 folders)
    - United States Army Corps of Engineers
      - Charts See also Oversize
        - Daily injections, 1962-1966, (2 folders)
        - Daily pressure recordings, undated, (2 folders) (Box 47)
        - Injection quantities, 1962
        - Water-level measurements, 1966-1968
        - Well-head pressure, 1962-1965
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1965-1967
      - Notes and miscellany, 1966, undated
    - United States Geological Survey
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1965-1968
      - Reports, 1966, (2 folders) (Box 48)
  - Federal Council for Science and Technology, 1967-1968
  - Geochemical Society, 1956
  - Geological Society of America
    - Committees
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Membership Policy, 1958
      - Committee on the Seventy-fifth Anniversary of the Society, 1959-1961
      - Committee on Honors and Awards
        - Apollo astronauts, 1971-1972
        - National Medal of Science
          - Correspondence, 1970-1974, (3 folders)
          - Notes and miscellany, 1970-1974
      - Committee on nominations, 1949-1950, 1959
      - Committee on the War Effort (World War II) (Box 49)
        - Background materials on Germany's use of geology during wartime
          - Articles, 1942
          - Correspondence, 1935
        - Camouflage information, 1942
        - Correspondence, 1942-1945, (7 folders)
        - Education and employment information, 1941-1943, undated
        - Draft, peacetime legislation, undated
      - Lists of geologists, 1942
        - Memoranda, 1938-1945
        - Notes and miscellany, 1942-1943, undated
        - Reports, 1942-1947, undated (Box 50)
        - Topographic guide, 1942
      - Executive Committee, 1951-1958, (2 folders)
    - Cordilleran section, 1966-1967
    - Correspondence
      - Miscellaneous, 1948-1974
      - Secretary of Society, 1935-1958, (8 folders)
    - Kirk Bryan Award, 1961
    - Meetings, 1963-1966, 1973
    - Penrose conference, 1970-1971 (Box 51)
    - Publications
      - Anniversary book, 1962
      - Bibliography on continental drift, 1971-1974
      - Manuscript reviews, 1970-1972
    - Rocky Mountain section, 1963-1967
  - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
    - Committees
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Geological Sciences, 1953-1960
      - Selection of a New President Committee, 1970
      - Visiting Committee on Geological Services, 1959-1970
    - Proposal, “A program for science in Harvard University,” 1966
    - Symposium in honor of Francis Birch, 1969-1970
  - Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind., summer institute in field geology, 1961
  - Instituto della Enciclopedia Italiana, 1974
  - Intermountain Association of Geologists, field trip, 1967
  - International Colloquium on Mars, 1973
  - International Geological Congress, 1959-1964
  - International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics, 1950
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry, 1953-1961
  - Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., 1958-1970
  - Joint Research and Development Board, 1947-1950 (Box 52)
  - Journal of Marine Research, 1960-1963
  - Lunar Science Institute
    - Advisory Committee, 1968-1971
    - Apollo 12 Lunar Science Conference, 1970-1971
    - Articles and newspaper clippings, 1969-1972
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1968-1974, (2 folders)
    - Library, 1969
    - Lists of papers published by members, 1971
    - Lunar Sample Review Board
      - Annual reports, 1971
      - Appointments to board, 1970-1971
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1970-1972
      - Meetings, 1970-1971, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1970-1974, undated (Box 53)
    - Newsletters, 1969-1971
    - Portraits of Lloyd Berber and Harry Hess, 1970-1971
    - Press releases, 1968-1970
    - Summer study on post-Apollo lunar science, 1972
    - Visiting professors' program, 1969-1973
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass., 1951-1960
  - McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia of Science and Technology, editorial advisory board, 1955-1974, undated, (6 folders)
  - Mohole project (Box 54)
    - American Miscellaneous Society Committee
      - Agreement re role of Committee, 1962-1963
      - Background materials re Soviet drilling, 1962-1963, (2 folders)
      - Correspondence and memoranda
        - 1957-1963, (9 folders)
        - 1963-1964, (3 folders) (Box 55)
      - Lists of members, 1958-1963
      - Minutes of meetings, 1957-1963, (5 folders)
      - Notes and miscellaneous lists, 1961-1965, undated
      - Panels
        - Drilling techniques, 1959-1963
        - Naval architecture, 1962-1963
        - Oceanic sediments drilling, 1962-1963
        - Scientific objectives and measurements, 1959-1963, (2 folders)
        - Site selection, 1960-1964 (Box 56)
      - Press releases, 1961-1964
      - Proposals, 1962-1963, (4 folders)
      - Reports, 1959-1963
      - Reviews of other reports, 1962-1963
    - Articles, 1957-1964, (3 folders)
    - Brown and Root, Inc. (Box 57)
      - Management plan and statement of qualifications, 1961, (2 folders)
      - Reports
        - Department of Navy
          - Abstract presentation to Bureau of Yards and Docks, 1964
          - Progress report, 1964
        - Engineering plans, 1963, (4 folders); (8 folders); (6 folders) (Box 58, Box 59)
        - Preliminary report, 1962
        - Scientific and technical progress reports, 1963-1964, (7 folders) (Box 60)
        - Weekly progress reports, 1962-1964, (3 folders) (Box 61)
    - Congressional floor statements, 1963-1966
    - Congressional hearings, 1963
    - Joint Oceanographic Institution, 1965
    - Miscellany
      - Correspondence, 1959-1966
      - Press releases and technical papers, 1943-1961, undated
    - National Science Foundation
      - Briefing sessions, 1961
      - Brochures, undated
      - Committees
        - Ad Hoc Committee to Review Proposed Programs for Drilling and Sampling the Oceanic Crust, 1963, undated, (4 folders)
        - Special National Science Board Committee on Oceanic Drilling, 1963 (Box 62)
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1960-1967, (4 folders)
      - Minutes of meetings, 1963-1965